sentikinesis
thymia
It is not allowed to hurt others with thymia.
不可以使用情念力來傷害他人
Every child in our mud whale
泥鯨上的孩子們
had been taught like this for long.
一直被這樣教育著
However,
但這次
we made up our minds to fight.
我們決心與敵人一戰
We had been training hard to protect ourselves
為了迎戰帝國戰艦斯奇洛斯
from the attack by the Empire's battleship, Skulax.
我們進行的訓練
But the training was just like some unfamiliar role playing games.
就像玩不慣的過家家一樣
Nevertheless, they were the utmost we could do.
即便如此 我們也是那麼的竭盡全力
And we were really serious.
那麼的一本正經
Thymia does not act directly on human beings.
情念力不能直接作用於人體
Therefore when we use its power,
所以我們使用力量的時候
we have to focus the forces on bows, arrows and blades.
需要把力量集中到弓箭或者刀劍上
That's it! Think about the shape of the bow in your mind.
對了 在腦子裡想像弓的形狀
Then image if you draw that bow.
想像使勁讓它彎曲的形象
Also don't forget the arrow!
也不要忘了箭啊
I won't forget!
不會忘的 卜回完的
Pull the string of the bow.
拉緊弓弦
Then look at the mark.
然後看向靶子
Look!
靶子 巴紙
Shoot the arrow over there.
把箭刺向那裡
Shoot!
那裡 拉裡
Even the bows that are too tight for the children,
小孩子們拉不動的弓
they can draw with the help of thymia.
藉助情念力的幫助也能拉動
It also benefits the accuracy.
命中精度也能上升
Moving the object itself
讓物體自身運動
is the basic usage of thymia.
是情念力最基本的用法
Hey you.
喂 你啊
Come here with us.
能跟我們一起出去一下嗎
What's up?
搞什麼啊 突然
Shut up!
你給我閉嘴
Dark-natured guy!
陰沉鬼
Dark-natured baldy!
陰沉禿鬼
What?
哎
Dark-natured record freak destroyer!
陰沉記錄魔毀滅者
No!
噫
Let's go!
我們走
Uhh...
嗚
Hey, are you guys OK?
沒事吧你們幾個
What's your purpose?
什麼事情
Bring them here.
拿過來
Your clothes are torn, right?
你衣服不是破了嗎
Shinono felt sorry and told us to choose some clothes for you.
希諾諾姐姐說看你好可憐讓我們幫你選選
This color suits your skin!
這個顏色跟你膚色很配的
This one is also cute!
這件也很可愛喲
I can't fight with them...
這怎麼去打仗啊…
May I trim it myself to make it fit me more?
感覺有點緊 我可以重新修剪一下嗎
Of course.
沒問題
I will lend you the sewing tools.
我借你裁縫工具
My name's Urumi, glad to see you.
你好 我叫烏露米
Don't stay with those guys, they are not cool at all.
別跟那幫不起眼的臭小子們在一起了
Let's be together!
跟我們一起行動多好
Yeah!
是吧
We are also confident with the performance of thymia.
我們對於操作情念力也很有自信
Yep.
嗯
Hey, tell us more about the enemies.
對了 告訴我們點敵人的事情
We want to fight together.
我們想一起戰鬥
...Because our...
我們的…
...our friends were killed.
朋友 被殺了
Nobody knows whether the route we take is correct.
誰也不可能清楚
But after 4 days, we will face the all-out attack from Skulax.
距離斯奇洛斯的總攻擊
Translator
翻
ssnake
譯
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
ssnake
Silence and melody, and the transient lives of Shirushi
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
時 間 軸
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
If you have been living on the land, on the sea of sand
如果是在這沙海之上  生活下去
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた...
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
In a sinned world, we have heard the whale's lied
在罪業重重的世界裡  我們曾側耳傾聽鯨魚的歌唱…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
Our fate and our emotions, my beloved children
不論命運  還是感情  親愛的孩子們喲
さ  き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
Towards the future, go ahead
向著未來  向著前方
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
If you can be our guide
只要有你指引前路
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
萬千寄語  向著空想的彼岸
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
Steering towards the opposite
相信信念調轉方向
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
萬千歡聲  是沙海的歌謠
F
雪 飄 工 作 室
L
雪 飄 工 作 室
That's Lasha-sama.
那不是拉夏奶奶
We have seldom seen her recently.
好久沒見到她了
But it wasn't that long since she joined the presbytery!
她進入長老會還沒多久吧
It has been... 2 years?
好像有…2年了？
But she is already tottering.
不過 腿腳已經踉踉蹌蹌的了
Assign members of the vigilante group to each team,
在各班裡分派警備團的成員
to train them.
負責訓練
And they should act together that day, so each team can be better protected.
當天也一起行動 兼作護衛
How about the members for that strategy?
那個作戰的成員呢？
The problem is,
麻煩的是
the shirushi loses their power of thymia
大多數「印」到25歲以後
after their mid-20s.
情念力的能力就大幅下滑了
We have no choice but make the children to fight...
只好拜託孩子們去拚命了
Children...
小孩們…
I will try find some people.
我去問幾個人看看
Lasha-sama...
拉夏奶奶
Do you feel good now?
您貴體可好嗎？
It's nothing about my feelings.
我身體怎麼樣都無所謂了
You were training the children, right?
看到你們在訓練小孩子們呢
Ye..yes...
嗯 是…
The new chief.
新首長
I've heard that your younger sister was killed by them.
你妹妹被他們殺了是吧？
You must hate the guys outside.
你恨著外面那幫傢伙沒錯吧
But you should never forget,
但是 可別忘了
the children may kill somebody tomorrow,
或許明天孩子們會殺人
the children may die tomorrow,
或許明天孩子們得去死
decided by you.
這都是「你」決定的
Lasha-sama,
拉夏奶奶
Suo cares about the children more than anyone else!
蘇澳比誰都要
Kuchiba,
庫奇巴
what about you?
你又是怎麼想的
You were together with Taisha,
你那時候跟台霞在一起
but you failed to protect her.
卻沒能保護好她
Don't you want a revenge?
所以打算打場復仇戰？
But you won't fight at all.
不過你是不會上戰場的
The children of shirushi die for you.
印的孩子們去為你犧牲而已
Kuchiba!
庫奇巴！
It's you presbytery's fault!
還不都怪你們長老會
You only made us to suicide together!
除了集體自殺什麼方案都拿不出來
If you have complaints...
對我們不滿的話…
I don't.
倒沒有
Do whatever you like.
隨你們怎麼做
Anyway, everything will come to an end soon.
反正不管怎麼樣一下子就結束了
And finally, the cursed children of the whale can be saved.
被詛咒的鯨魚的孩子們
Lasha-sama.
拉夏奶奶
We can only wait for the death if we do nothing.
什麼都不做的話就只能等死
We can't stop here and wait to die!
我們絕對不能止步不前
Oni.
歐尼
You were selected for the strategy of the chief, right?
你被選去參加首長的作戰行動了？
It's really dangerous.
那是很危險的任務吧
I'll bring something to eat.
我去拿點吃的來
Jiki, let's go.
基琪 跟我來
Oni suddenly appeared in a corner of the residential area someday.
歐尼他是不知何時
No one knows who is his parents.
誰都不知道他父母是誰
And he didn't belong to any team.
也不屬於任何一個班
That guy is always alone.
那傢伙一直都是一個人啊
I think he's name is Oni.
聽說叫歐尼
He's weird. Leave him alone.
奇怪的傢伙 別管他
Hey dude.
喂 你等等
I'll let you be my underling!
讓你當我小弟怎麼樣？
I mean let's play together!
我是讓你跟我一塊玩啊
Hey!
喂
Ah!
啊
You dare!
你這傢伙
Eh...
呃…
You idiot!
該死
Both of you violated the rule.
違反規則了 你們倆都是
Cuz this guy hit my face.
都怪這傢伙打我臉
I even bothered to ask him be my underling,
明明讓他當我小弟了
but he's cheeky...
還這麼猖狂
You have to live together in the internal for a few days.
你們倆先一起在體內待一段時間
It's a chance for you to talk with each other.
好好談談心
Damn, I hate it!
該死 討厭啊
Let me out!
放我出去
Why you want to be out that much?
你就這麼想出去嗎
They're the same, here and outside.
外面跟這不也是一樣的
It can never be the same!
才不一樣呢
You don't feel bad in such a small place?
你在這麼狹小的地方不覺得難受嗎
The island itself is small.
這個島都夠狹小了
We are surrounded by the sand, can't make a single move.
被沙海所圍困 一直動彈不得
We become adults and die, with ourselves cooped up in the island.
就這樣被封閉著變成大人然後去死
They're the same.
一回事
Then... Then why don't you go out!
只…只要能出去不就好了
You scum scum scum!
你這縮頭縮腦的蛆蟲
Get out of the island if you don't like it!
要是不爽 就從這島上滾出去啊
If you mean you can't go out,
要是你說做不到的話
I'll bring you out!
我來帶你出去
Umm, that's it!
嗯…對了
I decided!
決定了
You should be my underling!
果然你來當我小弟吧
Ah no, be my heeler.
啊不…當我手下
But, this is also the same...
不過 這也是一回事吧
I get it!
對了
Be my fellow!
當我的「夥伴」吧！
Then I'll bring you out!
肯的話就帶你到外面去
Hey you two, get out.
喂 你們倆都出來
You must hate to be sent to the internal.
不喜歡被送到體內吧
Learn from it, and never...
以此為戒 再也別…
But, it isn't that bad sometimes.
不過 偶爾進進也無所謂
Right?
是吧
Nibi, what will you do?
尼比 你要怎麼辦
Are you going to fight?
要戰鬥嗎？
I haven't given up my dream of going outside.
去外面的世界這件事 我可沒死心
I'll knock down every guy on that way,
礙事的傢伙全部幹掉
and bring you out!
一定會帶你去外面的
Don't forget I was the leader at the beginning!
本來我才是咱們的老大的
Yes you were.
是啊
I still think so.
我現在也是這麼覺得的
Cuz I'm one year older than you!
畢竟我比你大一歲
Stop laughing!
別笑
It was fun.
當年好開心啊
But...
不過…
We can never meet them again.
再也見不到他們倆了
Stop crying.
別哭
I can't!
我做不到！
I'm not as iron-minded as you.
我不像你那麼堅強
You are really amazing.
你是夠厲害的…
I've never seen you cry, for even a single time.
我一次都沒見你哭過
Oni.
歐尼
I... am a bit scaring.
我啊 總是有點害怕
I don't know where are you looking at,
不知道你的視線投向了什麼地方
and I don't know if you may leave us
害怕你哪一天丟下我們 自己一個人…
and go somewhere yourself...
到不知道什麼地方去了…
I won't.
我不會的
Tell me with your eyes on me!
看著我說啊
Oni!
歐尼
Chakuro.
查克羅…
Lykos.
黎可斯
You've changed clothes? It suits you.
你換衣服了？ 好適合你
Hmm?
嗯？
Take this.
這個
Because your clothes are worn-out...
你衣服 都破破爛爛了
I sewed it with the old clothes they gave me.
所以我把別人給我的舊衣服改了一下
You did it? For me?
黎可斯做的？給我的？
You don't need to wear if you don't like it.
不喜歡的話不穿就是了
Ah... Lykos?
啊 黎可斯？
After all...
果然…
The minds... are annoying.
果然有心靈…太礙事了
What are you doing here?
你們在做什麼？
We are gathering the sand.
我們在收集沙子 窩們在收席撒子
Cuz it's Sunamodori tomorrow.
因為明天是還沙日
We have finished 80% of the barricades on the east side.
東側的壁壘已經完成了八成左右
Although the west side is behind our schedule...
西側雖然有些延誤…
Suo?
蘇澳？
It is impossible...
看來不行呢
No,
不
If we assign those who without any works there,
把有空的人派過去的話
Sunamodori
還沙日
The Sunamodori on the west side...
西側的還沙日…
What!
啥？
At the moment facing the enemies,
在那幫傢伙們就要來的這關頭
how dare you think about playing with sands!
你還想著潑沙子玩？搞沒搞錯！
But...
可是…
The children should have been looking forward that...
雖然小傢伙們都很期待…
But it is impossible anyway~
不過果然不行啊～
More importantly, we have an assembly tomorrow.
倒是明天就要全體集會了
You must make up our minds in concert.
你得讓大家齊心協力
C'mon, chief-sama.
拜託了啊 首長先生
...Make sure you understand your position and role,
…各自妥善確認好自己負責的區域和任務
and prepare for anything that may happen.
準備好應對各種事態
This is the tactics for tomorrow.
以上就是我們明天的作戰計劃
There may be something horrible.
或許大家心存恐懼
There may be something sad.
或許大家難抑傷悲
But I wish,
但是
through the sky and the sea of sand,
跨越蒼穹與大海
our minds will always connect with each other.
我們的心靈始終 永遠連結在一起
When you are despaired and frightened,
當你陷入絕望 苦於恐怖之時
please remember my wish.
請不要忘記這個祈願
I wish we shall always be together,
願一切與你們相連的生命
with you and all the livings connected with you!
始終與你們心心相繫
Suo-sama!
蘇澳哥哥！
He has done well this time.
這次講得不錯呢
It was splendid!
很完美
Over there!
看那裡！
We completed it with over a year, just for this day!
為了今天我們工房費盡心血研究了整整一年
It's a masterpiece of our workshop!
終於完成了這件大傑作
Automatic sand-splashing machine.
自動潑沙機
And the name is...
其名為…
Automatic! Sand-splashing! Machine!
自動！潑沙！機！
Nothing changed at all.
這一個字都沒變
Maybe...
你們以為…
You thought whatever you do, I won't get angry at all.
對我做什麼我都不會生氣嗎…
You guys!
喂～！
Nezu! Lo! Chakuro!
涅茲！洛！查克羅！
He is more angry than we thought.
比我們預想的要生氣多了
Get down!
給我下來！
No problem,
沒關係
Suo is super bad at sports, we can definitely run away.
蘇澳運動神經超級差 咱們一定能順利逃走
I did get angry!
我也是會生氣的啊！
Push it!
快按
Wait!
給我等等！
Suo-sama has splashed sand!
蘇澳哥哥潑沙子了
It's Sunamodori!
還沙日開始了！
Hey... Wait!
喂 喂
Suo, stop them!
蘇澳 快讓他們住手
Huh?
咦
Enjoy it!
不客氣了！
The Sunamodori is an event held once a year.
還沙日
takes part in the battle and splashes sand onto others
這一天大家不分老少貴賤 都參與到潑沙大戰中來
until the sunset.
一直到太陽落山
And there is another meaning for the Sunamodori.
而且 還沙日還有另一個意義
The souls melted in the sand will come back to us
溶化在了沙海中的靈魂 會通過互相潑撒的沙子
through the splashed sand.
回到我們的身邊
Sami...
莎米…
Sorry I'm smiling so soon after you die.
你離世還沒有幾天
But I have never forgotten you.
不過 我是不會忘記你的
I will remember you ever and forever.
今後也會永遠記住你
Please keep watching me.
請在我身邊好好看著吧
What's up, Sienna?
怎麼了 希艾娜
You...
老公…
I have to take part in the battle.
我也要去參加戰鬥
The presbytery has ordered me.
長老會下了命令
Please prepare for your suicide.
你準備好自殺
I don't want your dead body to be ugly.
屍體不好看可不行
Does your heart feel nothing?
你心裡一點感觸都沒有嗎
Hmm?
嗯？
You cares only about whether the death of your wife is ugly?
你關心的就只有妻子死得好不好看嗎？
The feelings of people
人的感受什麼的
can never be shaped and visible.
難道是能化作實體看得見的東西嗎
Why you cares about the heart
你為什麼會這麼關心
that nobody really knows?
誰都說不清道不明的心靈呢？
Neli?
奈莉？
Thank goodness, you are all right.
太好了 你沒事啊
I wonder after those happened to Fallaina...
法萊那那之後 你怎麼…
You are not Neli?
不是奈莉…？
Who are you?
你是誰？
Where is Neli?
奈莉在哪裡？
That girl has returned to Mom's tummy.
那孩子回到媽媽肚子裡去了
To heal Mom's wounds.
為了治療媽媽的傷
Mom?
媽媽？
What is Mom...
媽媽是…
You can hear my voice clearly?
你能聽清我的聲音啊
Great!
太好了
I haven't talked with people for a long time.
我好久沒跟人說話了
Neli and I are twin. We share the same blood.
我啊 跟奈莉是雙胞胎
αίμα
αίμα
Call me Emma.
叫我「艾瑪」
Emma?
艾瑪…？
That's right, Mr. Recording clerk.
沒錯 記錄員
Hey, promise me.
吶 我想跟你約定
Wha... What? Promise?
哇 什…什麼？ 約定？
Protect the island at any cost.
絕對要保護好這座島
You said you'll protect everybody in the underground.
你在地下不是說要保護好大家的嗎
Forever... Let's live together forever!
永～遠…永遠讓大家一起活下去
I promise
這是我們的約定
if you can survive,
要是你活下來了
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
I will tell you all the secrets of Fallaina!
我就把法萊那的祕密全部告訴你
You mean the history of the mud whale?
你是說泥鯨的歷史嗎？
You know it?
你知道的嗎？
Emma, who are you and Neli?
艾瑪 你跟奈莉到底是什麼人？
What are you trying to tell me?
想要告訴我什麼
July 17, 93 S.S.
沙刑曆93年 7月17日
Confirmed a fog caused by the sand dust, before dawn.
黎明前 觀測到飛揚的沙塵造成的煙霧
After the sunrise, there was a sandstorm on the sea.
日出之後 海中出現沙暴
And the visibility was completely obstructed on the sea.
海上的視野被遮蔽得更加嚴重
We mud whale will intercept the enemies!
泥鯨從現在起開始迎擊敵人
The most important thing is,
最重要的是
to protect yourselves from the attacks by the enemies.
要保護好大家的生命 不被敵襲所害
Hold back the enemies as long as possible, fight them back if possible.
盡可能久地頂住敵人 將其擊退
Our goal is to survive.
我們的目的是保全性命
And another thing for you.
此外還有一點
While we are in defense,
在我們進行防禦作戰的時候
I ask you to penetrate into the emenies' battleship.
請各位潛入到敵人的戰艦中
And destroy Nous the Skulax inside the ship.
並且破壞艦內的魂形·斯奇洛斯
Sink their ship.
讓船沉沒
It's a very dangerous task.
這個任務十分危險
Therefore I only gathered those who with high ability of thymia.
所以 我匯集了情念力能力高超的各位
They are the charms I made.
這是我親手編的護身符
They were used for stuffs like hunting, praying for safety.
雖然本來是祈願狩獵安全的
Anyway please get it.
還請各位戴上
Please come back safely.
請務必安全回來
Yes, Suo-sama...
好的 蘇澳哥哥
Good girl, that's a good reply!
真乖真乖 答得真好
Thanks.
謝謝
Be careful.
請當心啊
I don't need it.
不需要
But...
可是…
Shut up.
真煩
This is not good. Have it!
這可不行 一定要戴上
I'm the captain of Team 3 of vigilante group. My name is Tokusa.
我是警備團第三班班長 托庫薩
And I'm the captain of this assault team.
是這次突擊隊的隊長
Let's cooperate together and respect each other!
不要破壞團結 讓我們一起齊心協力吧
Oni-kun!
歐尼同志
Thank you, Tokusa.
拜託你了 托庫薩
Don't say that, Suo-sama.
別這麼見外嘛 蘇澳小哥哥
Aren't we friends! Trust me please!
我們不是好朋友嗎 請相信我啊
Yes...
是…
Lykos,
黎可斯
you are already a member of the mud whale.
你已經是泥鯨的一員了
Care more about yourself.
多保重自己
Please be sure to survive and come back!
請你一定要活著回來
Yes.
是
Good girl, a good reply!
真乖真乖 說得真好
Chakuro,
查克羅
since you're the only ones who have seen the Nous...
你是少數見過魂形的人 我只能…
Don't worry, Suo.
別擔心 蘇澳
Leave it to us!
交給我們吧
Thank you, Chakuro.
謝謝你 查克羅
When you finished the loading,
東西都裝好了以後
board on the ship in order and wait for the next instruction!
依次上竹葉扁舟待命
I'll go with you!
我也去！
Nibi, you are not elected.
尼比 你沒被選上
Remain here and protect Kicha and others.
留下來 保護好綺茶他們
I've had enough! Don't leave me alone!
不要 我已經受夠被丟下了
Nibi-kun, thank you for your willing but...
尼比同志 很感謝你的意願 但是…
Shut up! Don't talk to me, you idiot vigilante!
別吵 該死的警備團給我閉嘴！
Calm down.
冷靜
Hey, haven't you heard anything?
喂 你們沒聽到什麼聲音嗎
There are sounds other than the sandstorm.
沙暴以外有什麼東西在響
What?
什麼
They are coming...
…來了
The enemies, they are right there!
敵人 就在我們附近！
The sixth section
第 六 節
The fifth section
第 六 節
They may kill somebody tomorrow
或 許 明 天
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
Staring into the trace of the dried sea
眺望昔日的大海
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
I will draw the other side I have never seen
描繪未知的彼岸
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
If you remain your heart in captivity
如果囚禁起心靈  一如過往
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
You may live without knowing the pain
又怎會經歷如此悲傷
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
The one who told the beautiful story
是誰講述起美好的希望
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
Can not wait for the dawn
讓我等不及黎明
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
向著天涯海角揚帆起航
虫の唄
虫の唄
Listen to the insects' song
徹夜蟲鳴
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
That night is our memory
回憶裡與你一起側耳傾聽
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
Just link hand in hand
只是雙手相牽
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
不論夕陽  還是遠方
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
Born in a short chapter
在這短暫蒼渺的一章裡
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう
But let us go and embrace that dream
一起追逐夢想
The seventh section
第 七 節
I want to see your future
我 想 看 到